Finding Aid for Allmendinger Family Papers, 1824-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allmendinger Family Papers 1824-2006 1890-1986
Allmendinger family.
8525 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Ann Arbor German-American family, owners of the Allmendinger Organ Company which later became the Ann Arbor Organ Company. Correspondence, scrapbooks, family genealogy, photographs concerning family affairs, materials on Helene Allmendinger's radio show, examples of spirit messages received by Helene Allmendinger from deceased family members; information pertaining to the Ann Arbor Organ Company, and family members still living in Germany.
8 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Allmendinger family members (donor nos. 5606, 9434, 10257 ).
The collection is open to research.
David F. and Marie (nee Garttner) Allmendinger were long-time residents of Ann Arbor, Michigan. David Allmendinger (1848-1916) emigrated from Germany in 1851 at the age of three. He was trained as a cabinet-maker and later learned the craft of organ manufacture. In 1872, he started his own business, the Allmendinger Organ Company, which later became the Ann Arbor Organ Company. His son Herman D. Allmendinger (1873-1945) worked with the company, then in 1915, he established his own business, the Allmendinger Music Shop which he managed until he sold the firm in 1929. Another of David and Marie's children, Helene Allmendinger (1878-1973), was a singer, composer of music, and a Spiritualist.
The collection is divided into the following series: Family records and correspondence; Helene Allmendinger papers; Ina Allmendinger papers; Ann Arbor Organ Company; Harriet Birch papers, Other family members; Miscellaneous, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Allmendinger family.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Organ Company.; German Americans--Michigan.; Germany.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Radio broadcasting--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Spirit writings.; Spiritualism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Allmendinger, David Fredrich, 1848-1916.; Allmendinger, Helen Sophie, 1878-1973.; Allmendinger family.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Arbeiter Verein.; Ann Arbor Organ Company.; Children.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Families--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gardens--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; German Americans--Michigan.; Interiors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Kolberg, Marie Allmendinger, 1875-1973.; Laboring classes.; Offices--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Weddings.; Working class.
Contributors: Manuscripts
Allmendinger, Ina.; Allmendinger, David Friedrich, 1848-1916.; Allmendinger, Helene Sophie, 1878-1973.; Birch, Harriet A.
Genre Terms:
Glass negatives.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Audiotapes.
- Family records and correspondence
  Family records and correspondence includes family history information collected and compiled by Ina Allmendinger, wife of Martin N. Allmendinger. Genealogical research materials produced by other members of the family comprise portions of the series. This series also contains family correspondence, sometimes referred to as "round robins" by the Allmendingers. These letters were sent between extended family members, frequently as a form letter, but were also addressed to specific family members. In casual correspondence between family members, these letters were often referred to as "R.R.," for "round robin." Family records and correspondence also includes material from Marie Garttner and other relatives on the maternal side of the D.F. Allmendinger family.
  - Records of the Allmendinger Family in Europe (Box 1)
  - Military Service Records 1918-1970 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Family Record Questionnaires and Correspondence 1948-1981 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - A History of the George David Branch of the Allmendinger Family 1935 (Box 1)
    (written by Clara Allmendinger)
  - Bethlehem Cemetery, Ann Arbor 1889-1923 (Box 1)
  - Assorted family documents, scattered dates (Box 1)
  - Kinship of David Frederick Allmendinger 2004 (Box 1)
    (includes name, date of birth, and relationship to D.F. Allmendinger)
  - Allmendinger lineage 1997 (Box 1)
  - Allmendinger Family Tree circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - Allmendinger Family histories (Box 1)
    (includes eulogy for David F. Allmendinger)
  - Commercial Allmendinger family history materials and related correspondence 1981 (Box 1)
  - Maternal Ancestors (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence, undated 1890-1929, 1940-1974, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence
    (Round robin)
    - 1923-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1961-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-2003 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence 1935-1971 (Box 1)
    (not D.F. Allmendinger family)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1843-1871 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Family reunion correspondence 1923-1995 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries (Box 1)
  - Marie Garttner
    - German diaries 1861-1864, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - French and English exercise book undated (Box 1)
    - German language academic certificates 1862-1864 (Box 1)
    - German language papers circa 1861 (Box 1)
    - German language material (Box 1)
      (German liturgy)
  - Collected records of Helene A., Julia, and Otto Allmendinger (Box 2)
    (includes correspondence, clippings, and questionnaires)
  - Compiled "per family" data (Box 2)
    (Louise Charlotte, Marie E. Herman David, and Pauline Rosina Christiana Allmendinger, as well as the Dalke family)
  - Collected records of Clara, Ruth, Olga (died as infant), and Victor Allmendinger (Box 2)
    (includes correspondence and questionnaires)
  - Family history questionnaires for Rosa, Emma Cornelia, and Martin Allmendinger (Box 2)
    (minimal correspondence)
  - Allmendinger Family Historians Reference Book 1975 (Box 2)
  - D.F. Allmendinger Family History 1950 (Box 3)
    (prepared by Ina Allmendinger)
  - Ina Allmendinger's duplicate copy of the Allmendinger Family History (Box 3)
    (with annotations and document originals)
  - Family tree scroll (Box 3)
  - Genealogical chart (Folder 1)
  - Certificates and diplomas (Folder 1)
- Helene Allmendinger papers
  The Helene Allmendinger papers contain material related to her musical career, as well as her interest in and practice of Spiritualism. Biographical material is available in the form of scrapbooks and diaries. Helene Allmendinger is heavily represented in the photograph series, which provides additional biographical context. The series also includes correspondence with friends, fans of her musical performances on the WJR radio station, as well as some family correspondence.
  - Correspondence with Oluf Petersen (cousin) 1900-1935 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Thomas A. MacBirney 1907-1908 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Vivian Small 1913 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with "Hans," 1913-1916 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Emil Schmidt 1916-1918 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with "Laddie" (James Hall?) 1920 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) 1916-1947 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous family correspondence 1929-1973 (Box 4)
    (includes 1929 letter discussing family tensions regarding money)
  - Correspondence with government officials 1940-1970 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Mrs. William Trent 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with E.P. Hill 1955-1957 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Muller family in Europe 1946-1973 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence concerning Helene Allmendinger's W.J.R. radio show 1928 (Box 4)
  - High School grades 1890-1899 (Box 4)
  - Prayers 1936-1973 (Box 4)
  - Poems 1925-1972 (Box 4)
  - Music career 1910 (Box 4)
  - Spiritualist writings 1930s, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Records of Spiritualist meditation sessions
    - 1932-1936 (Box 4)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 4)
    - 1939, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Collected Spiritualist items (Box 4)
  - Spiritualist sermons 1935 (Box 4)
  - Helene Allmendinger scrapbook containing clippings, programs of her performances, photographs, and memorabilia, circa 1899-1957 (Box 4)
  - Legal and financial records, miscellaneous 1909-1973 (Box 5)
    (some regarding Helene Allmendinger estate)
  - Account books and receipts, miscellaneous 1898-1989 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - "In lieu of last will and testament," 1965 (Box 5)
  - Non-Allmendinger news clippings 1934-1936 (Box 5)
  - Stories, undated (Box 5)
  - Radio programs 1920-1929 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Musical compositions, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Diaries 1900-1972 (multiple volumes) (Box 5)
- Ina Allmendinger papers
  The Ina Allmendinger papers contain two sub-series, Correspondence and Family History. Correspondence consists of letters to and from Ina and various D.F. Allmendinger descendants. As Family Historian, Ina prepared and mailed out Family History Questionnaires to the extended Allmendinger family, in an effort to collect genealogical data. As a result, much of the correspondence included in her papers relate to family history. The Family History sub-series consists of non-correspondence items that illustrate some aspect of Allmendinger history, both in Germany and the U.S.
  - Correspondence
    - DeBruyn family in Europe 1946 (Box 6)
    - Van Santen family in Europe 1946-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - European relatives 1946-1973 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1868-1871, undated (Box 6)
      ("Old Morgan papers")
    - Helene Muller 1947-1982 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
      (includes letters from Paul Burk to Helene Muller)
    - Julia Allmendinger Murray family 1964-2003 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Pauline Rosina Christine Allmendinger Dalke 1969-2004 (Box 6)
      (includes letters from Paul Dalke and Dorothy Meyers)
    - Harriet Birch and other Birch family members 1970-1989 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Louise Charlotte Allmendinger family 1973-1980 (Box 6)
      (bulk of correspondence is between Ina and Ruth McClusky Jones)
    - David Allmendinger, Jr. 1974-1980 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
      (includes correspondence regarding transfer of family records to the Bentley Historical Library)
    - Herman David Allmendinger family 1974-1980 (Box 6)
    - Eleanor Schmidt Dorstewitz and family 1974-1989 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Clara Allmendinger Rebert family 1974-1986 (Box 6)
      (scattered dates)
    - Cita van Santen 1974-1986 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence 1976-1984 (Box 6)
    - Emrick family 1976-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Helene Allen and family 1977-1989 (Box 6)
    - Gaerttner family (Box 6)
      (Donald and Georgia)
    - Virginia Forseman Tesh 1985 (Box 6)
      (descendents of Victor A. Allmendinger)
    - General correspondence 1989 (Box 6)
  - Family History
    - Family history materials (Box 6)
    - Allmendinger family genealogy, 3 folders (Box 6)
      (includes German map of Stuttgart with underlined locations of family interest)
    - Non-Allmendinger news clippings (Box 6)
- Ann Arbor Organ Company
  Ann Arbor Organ Company includes assorted correspondence, background information and articles, as well as material pertaining to business operations of the company. News clippings about the company can also be found in the series.
  - Catalogs, specifications, drawings, and financial materials, 3 folders; 1 volumes (Box 6)
    (see also oversize folder Ac)
  - Background information and articles 1915-1992 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1965-2006 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    (includes photo of a non-Allmendinger organ)
  - News clippings 1947-1993 (scattered) (Box 6)
- Harriet Birch papers
  The Harriet Birch papers include family correspondence between Allmendinger relatives. Harriet (1922-2008), a granddaughter of David F. Allmendinger, was the daughter of Floyd Wuerth and Rosa Allmendinger Wuerth. Her papers consist of correspondence to Allmendinger descendents in Germany, as well as to Ina Allmendinger and Eleanor Dorstewitz. Biographical information is also available, including a "Life Reading" that Harriet ordered from a Washington state couple.
  - Biographical 1941-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
  - Ina Allmendinger, correspondence 1980-1999 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
  - Family Correspondence 1980-2005 (Box 7)
  - Muller family history and related correspondence 1985-1995 (Box 7)
    (includes correspondence between Don Gaerttner and Dorothy Wagner)
  - Muller family correspondence 1987-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
    (to Harriet and Carol Birch; includes photographs)
  - Eleanor Schmidt Dorstewitz, correspondence 1999-2003 (Box 7)
- Other family members
  Other family members contains material from other Allmendinger family members, including a memoir (both finished and manuscript version) from Ruth Allmendinger Schmidt, correspondence from Rosa Wuerth concerning the old-age care of Marie Kolberg, correspondence from Don and Georgia Gaerttner, extended family of Marie Garttner, wife of D.F. Allmendinger, and records of the Wagner and Murray families.
  - Allmendinger family miscellanea (Box 7)
  - D.F. Allmendinger family scrapbooks, 2 volumes; 1 folders (Box 7)
  - Martin Allmendinger, family scrapbook (Box 7)
  - Memoir, "This is the story of my life," by Ruth Allmendinger Schmidt (Box 7)
  - Manuscript, "This is the story of my life," by Ruth Allmendinger Schmidt 1962 (Box 7)
    (typewritten manuscript; includes photographs)
  - Supplemental material on David F. Allmendinger, Jr. (Box 7)
    (David F. Allmendinger Conference Center)
  - Immigration Resources Project 1976-1997 (Box 7)
  - Rosa Wuerth, correspondence 1967-1973 (Box 7)
    (regarding care of Marie Kolberg)
  - Gaerttner and Peterson correspondence 1985-1991 (Box 7)
  - Wagner and Murray records 1989-1991 (Box 7)
    (includes legal documents regarding Dorothy Wagner estate)
  - Wuerth family correspondence 2004, undated (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous includes printed matter about the Limpert family (Ina Allmendinger's maiden name was Limpert), assorted miscellanea, and documents from the Washtenaw Abstract Company. Also includes an audio tape recording of an interview with Helene Allmendinger.
  - Washtenaw Abstract Company, Statement of Title and Deeds 1824-1944 (Box 7)
  - Clippings and invitations (Box 7)
  - Limpert family, printed matter 1937, 2004 (Box 7)
    (Ina Allmendinger's maiden name)
  - Audiotape of interview with Helene Allmendinger conducted by Johanna Wiese circa 1960s (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contain photographs of the David F. Allmendinger family, as well as more recent snapshots and portraits from his scattered descendants. For the six folders of photos of the D.F. Allmendinger family, 1881-1943, the donor has supplied identifications. In addition, the donor assigned identification numbers to these images. Helene, Charles, George F., Marie, David F., Robert C., and Rosa Allmendinger are among the family members depicted in the photographs. Photographs of Marie Kolberg, Harriet Birch, and the Karl Muller family are also included. Pictures of the Ann Arbor Organ Company also comprise a part of this series.
  - Class of 1936 (Box 7)
    (copy; names supplied on reverse)
  - Allmendinger Conference on Genealogy 1997 (Box 7)
    (at Weber's restaurant in Ann Arbor)
  - Muller family photographs circa 1948-1990 (Box 7)
  - Rosa Allmendinger Wuerth circa 1912 (Box 7)
    (includes photocopy of print of Wuerth Theater, Ann Arbor, ca. 1940)
  - Harriet A. Birch undated (Box 7)
    (copies of originals)
  - Family Reunions 1993-1997 (Box 7)
    (several negatives available)
  - Julia A. Murray family circa 1940-1970 (Box 7)
  - Family snapshots and portraits (Box 7)
  - Family and Allmendinger Organ Shop photograph album (Box 8)
  - D.F. Allmendinger family 1881-1943, 6 folders
    (identifications and identification nos. supplied by the donor)
    - D. F. Allmendinger (Box 8)
      (photo no. 1)
    - Family group in garden May 22, 1898 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 2)
    - English Lutheran Choir (Mary and Louise) May 22, 1898 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 3)
    - Decoration Day circa May 3, 1898 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 4)
    - Hat Shop Girls May 19, 1897 Louise (Box 8)
      (photo no. 5)
    - Decoration Day circa May 3, 1898 River scene (Box 8)
      (photo no. 6)
    - "The Old Country School," December 5, 1895 Benefit (Box 8)
      (photo no. 7)
    - Allmendinger Garden 1895 Boat and lake (Box 8)
      (photo no. 8)
    - Allmendinger Garden, about 1895 Layout view (Box 8)
      (photo no. 9)
    - Allmendinger Garden 1896 Summer, boat on lake (Box 8)
      (photo no. 10)
    - Christmas, family group 1899 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 11)
    - Allmendinger home, rear view 1896 Where the hollyhocks bloom (Box 8)
      (photo no. 12)
    - Allmendinger gardens-lakes 1901 Lotus Garden (Box 8)
      (photo no. 13)
    - Allmendinger gardens 1901 "A Dream of Paradise" (Box 8)
      (photo no. 14)
    - Allmendinger gardens 1901 Fountain in Pond (Box 8)
      (photo no. 15)
    - Allmendinger gardens - Trees reflected in pond (Box 8)
      (photo no. 16)
    - Family group on small bridge (Box 8)
      (photo no. 17)
    - Allmendinger gardens August 24, 1902 Family group in summer house (Box 8)
      (photo no. 18)
    - Mother and Marie at Niagara Falls August 1901 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 19)
    - Six girls on front steps-Ruth, Clara, Rosa, Cornelia, Lou and Marguerite (Box 8)
      (photo no. 20)
    - Helene S. Allmendinger August 15, 1901 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 21)
    - Helene S. Allmendinger July, 1881 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 22)
    - Helene S. Allmendinger June 21, 1899 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 23)
    - Robert Charles Allmendinger 1922 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 24)
    - Robert Charles Allmendinger 1943 U.S. Army Air Force (Box 8)
      (photo no. 25)
    - Arbeiter Verein Anniversary, July, 18-Louise A. and another woman on either end of celebration banner (Box 8)
      (photo no. 26)
    - Allmendinger gardens-Summer house, rustic (group) (Box 8)
      (photo no. 27)
    - "First Church of the Germans in Michigan," (Trans.) 1881 Identifications on back (Box 8)
      (photo no. 28)
    - Marie Allmendinger and daughters August 29, 1907 Identifications on back (Box 8)
      (photo no. 29)
    - D. F. Allmendinger and sons (cabin) August 29, 1907 Identifications on back (Box 8)
      (photo no. 30)
    - D. F. Allmendinger and family, August 29, 1907- Identifications on back (Box 8)
      (photo no. 31)
    - D. F. Allmendinger and sons (Box 8)
      (photo no. 32)
    - Car decorated with banner advertising the Allmendinger Music Shop 1915 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 33)
    - Horse-drawn wagon decorated as parade float and advertising the Allmendinger Music Ship 1915 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 34)
    - Ann Arbor Arbeiter Verein members 1894 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 35)
    - D. F. Allmendinger family under oak tree on their property 1907 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 36)
    - Columbus oak tree on D. F. Allmendinger property (Box 8)
    - Baptist Church choir June 18, 1899 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 38)
    - Helene Allmendinger, Chicago 1905 first formal gown (Box 8)
      (photo no. 39)
    - Helene Allmendinger, Chicago 1905 (Box 8)
      (photo no. 40)
    - Helene Allmendinger, Chicago Opera Company, as Martha in Faust 1907, 3 portraits (Box 8)
      (photo no.41)
    - Helene Allmendinger 1912 Paris gown (Box 8)
      (photo no. 42)
    - Helene Allmendinger, Oakland, California 1922, 3 portraits (Box 8)
      (photo no. 43)
    - Helene Allmendinger, Davenport, Iowa, 2 portraits (Box 8)
      (photo no. 44)
  - Helene Allmendinger picture book 1917-1920 (Box 8)
  - Helene Allmendinger miscellaneous photographs 1906-1940 (Box 8)
  - Helene Allmendinger last years 1960-1971 (Box 8)
  - Personal family photos 1935-1971 (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor Organ Company photos (Box 8)
  - Karl Müller family photos 1964 (Box 8)
  - German photos 1940-1958 (Box 8)
  - Charles G. Allmendinger (Box 8)
  - Helene Allmendinger's Voice Teacher (Box 8)
  - George Frank Allmendinger (Box 8)
  - Photoprints of negatives; include family reunion circa 1920 and family portraits, 1907 (Box 8)
  - Marie Allmendinger Kolberg Photo album (Volume 1)